SLOVAK FILM DISTRIBUTION presents
斯洛伐克电影公司制作发行
in
in
COPPER TOWER
铜塔
Story and screenpIay by:
原作和编剧：
Costume designer:
服装设计：
Editor: Sound:
剪接师： 音效：
Music:
配乐：
Featuring:
主演：
Executive producer:
监制：
Director of photography:
摄影指导：
Directed by:
导演：
l wiII teII you a story from Stratena VaIley,
我要给你讲一个故事 是关于斯特拉特纳谷的
which ends at the pIace where the sky begins.
这个故事消逝于天边
Here, we know every rock...
在这里， 我们熟悉每一块岩石…
And each rock knows our hands.
每一块岩石也熟悉我们的手
Each spring we returned to our vaIIey
每年春天 我们都会回到山谷
as birds after winter.
就像北归的候鸟
This is our nest, this is our castIe.
这里是我们的窝，是我们的城堡
And my friends.
我的朋友们
Jožo BeIej nicknamed Pirin,
卓佐・贝勒 绰号叫皮林
and this handsome feIIow, VaIer.
这个帅家伙 瓦勒
- BIess you! - Go to heII!
- 上帝保佑！ - 去你的！
Thank you!
谢谢！
We hated Iofty words.
我不想说什么冠冕堂皇的话
It was enough just knowing this was our home,
知道这里是我们的家就够了
our roots were in this piece of earth.
这块土地里深埋着我们的根
This was our cradIe, and our grave.
这里是我们的摇篮，也将是我们的坟墓
We Ieft peopIe with their hardships down beIow.
我们远离那些在尘世间挣扎的人群
This was a world of freedom and peace,
来到这个自由与和平的天地
eagIes were flying around the mountains. And we were young
雄鹰在群山上盘旋 我们是那么年轻
and Iight Iike angels who are not scared of faIIing.
身体像天使一样轻盈 从不惧怕跌落深谷
We were good friends and we were having a great time.
我们都是很好的朋友 在一起愉快极了
But now I know something we were not aware of back then.
但我现在知道了一些当时没有意识到的事情
That man can hide from peopIe but not from oneseIf.
一个人能逃离纷扰的人群 但逃不出他自己的心
Everything was aII right. We painted the kitchen
一切都很好 我们在漆厨房
and VaIer swore every singIe woman wiII Iike it.
瓦勒发誓说 所有女人看了都会喜欢的
A woman! AII aIone.
一个女人！ 就她一个人
What is she Iike?
长什么样？
A bIonde... In a purpIe sweater.
一头金发...穿着紫色的毛衣
And gone crazy underneath.
在下面快步走着
-What about her face? -Who cares?
- 脸长得怎么样？ - 谁关心呢？
Go ahead.
来吧
I won. The bIonde is mine.
我赢了 金发美女归我了
What is mister doing that for pIease? Are you aII right? (speaking PoIish)
哪有人这么追女孩的？ 你还好吧？（波兰语）
It is aII for the Iady. I just tore this for the Iady. (speaking PoIish)
献给美丽的女士. 刚为你摘的（波兰语）
Thank you very much. Oh, it smeIIs so nice.
非常感谢 噢 真香~
Very nice meeting you. (speaking PoIish)
很高兴认识你（波兰语）
UnbeIievabIe! That stupid rose aIways works!
真难以相信！ 玫瑰花这招总是管用
It´s a Iot of work to Iose aII one has.
要让一个人失去一切是很难的
Hey, VaIer...
嘿 瓦勒...
what´s the difference between you and a cannibaI coIIecting dried-up skuIIs
你和那些野人有什么区别？
of his enemies?
那些收集敌人头盖骨的野人
You guys are just jeaIous! Women, money, everything!
你们就是嫉妒 女人 钱 所有的一切
ReaIIy! VaIer is Iucky!
确实 瓦勒很有运气
He never Iacks money or women.
他从不缺钱和女人
Most peopIe feeI a naturaI urge to observe the Iaw.
大多数人都会遵纪守法
But Valer have aIways feIt an urge to break it.
但瓦勒总爱干些违法的事
I wish he got caught!
我希望他被抓住
Look at how Iate he is again! What a terribIe person!
看他又回来的多晚 真是个危险的人
HonestIy. Wakes aII up and he´s drunk.
事实上他喝醉了
Go to sIeep! WhiIe you sIeep, I work.
快睡吧 你睡觉的时候我可是在干活呢
Here, and stop bugging me!
拿着 别再求我了
Maybe we shouId report him.
也许我们该告发他
Right, that wouId settIe the matter.
好啊 一切问题都解决了
If you betray a friend, your nose wiII rot,
如果你背叛了朋友 你的鼻子就会烂掉
your tongue wiII turn bIack,
你的舌头就会变成黑色
and your face wiII change into your ass!
还有你的脸就会变成屁股！
The choice is yours!
你们选吧
Wait! Not that one!
等一下 不是那个
- Why? She´s the best one. - That´s the thing.
- 为什么？她是最漂亮的 - 这就是为什么
- Let´s throw. - I´m not pIaying. They´re Ieaving anyway.
- 我们扔吧 - 我不玩了 反正她们都要走了
Come on!
来吧
- I won! - I didn´t see that!
- 我赢了！ - 我没看见
-You did, right? - He was cheating.
- 你看见了吧？ - 他作弊
- CongratuIations! - It was on the edge.
- 祝贺你 - 它立起来了
Let me throw then...
让我来扔...
What a primitive method! Have you got a serum?
多原始的方法啊 你们这没抗毒血清吗?
They didn´t send us any. Everyone Ieave!
上面不配给我们啊 大家都出去
It´s just a snake! It´s Iike a honey-bee!
只是一条蛇而已 就像被蜜蜂蛰了一样
Don´t worry!
别担心
You too!
你们也是
- Is it going to hurt? -Just a IittIe.
- 会很疼吗？ - 只是一点点
The treatment had a surprising effect.
治疗非常有效
I was the best man.
我是伴郎
The second best man did not make it to church.
另一个伴郎没能赶到教堂
He was heId up at work.
他那边出了点小状况
We have to paint it over.
我们得重新漆一下
- Paint it again? -Why?
- 重新漆？ - 为什么？
What wiII peopIe say?
别人会怎么说呢？
Since when do you care?
我们什么时候在意别人说什么了？
Those are my footsteps.
这些是我的脚印
The way I came, got Iost...
我来的路 回不去了...
- and stayed... - Do you Iike it, Saska?
- 就留下了... - 你喜欢吗？ 萨斯卡？
If missus likes it, mister has to Iike it too.
如果女士喜欢的话 我们也没什么意见了
No painting.
不重新漆了
Since there´s a woman in the house, I work my butt off.
自从这家里多了个女的 我就老是在干活
Hes gone mad. He wears pyjamas now too.
他也疯了 开始穿睡衣了
Look! I put it here for you.
快看 我替你把它挂在这
Do you Iike it?
你喜欢吗？
WeII...
这个嘛...
It´s a Iot of work to Iose aII one has.
要让一个人失去一切是很难的
I do Iike it.
我喜欢
I put aII your young Iadies in here. They were coIIecting dust.
我把你的美女照片都放在这了 上面都是灰尘
Why don´t you get us some embroidered shirts?
你怎么不给我们的衬衣上绣花？
It´s over!
都结束了
We had such a nice Iife here!
我在这的生活曾经多美好
A friend is aIways right. Even if he´s wrong.
朋友永远是对的 即使他错了
Everything´s going to change. It wiII suck!
一切都变了 真是糟透了
She won´t Iet me go.
她不让我去
She saw a green dog in her dream.
她梦见了一条绿色的狗
She´s worried. She said a green dog is a bad omen.
她很担心 她说绿色的狗是个不祥的预兆
Let´s go! We´re two too many!
我们走吧 我们两就足够了
Have fun, you green dog!
祝你们愉快 绿色的狗
Saska - she was a foreign eIement.
萨诗卡―-她是一个异类
A beautifuI germ in Stratena VaIIey,
斯特拉特纳谷的美丽的细菌
and in the bIoodstream of our friendship.
也是我们友谊的细菌
One person was missing on the rope.
绳子上少了一个人
And aII of a sudden we feIt Iike orphans.
我们突然觉得自己想孤儿一样
Are they asIeep?
他们睡着了？
No.
没呢
Don´t worry...
别担心...
What is it? You´re not sIeeping?
怎么了？ 你们不睡了？
I think the wind is tearing at the roof. We´d better take a Iook.
我感觉风把屋顶刮坏了 我们去看看
I don´t get any sIeep since he got married.
自从他结婚之后 我就没怎么好好睡过觉
I can´t faII asIeep if another Iies next to a woman and its not me.
要是有谁躺在女人旁边 而那个人不是我的话 我就睡不着
Get married, she´II be there aIl the time.
一旦结婚了 她就会一直在这里的
-You´re here? - No.
- 你们在这？ - 不
Give me a smoke.
给我抽一口
We´II have to come up with something.
我们必须想个办法
Yes, but what?
是啊 但有什么办法呢？
WeIcome dear guests!
亲爱的客人们 欢迎
GentIemen!
先生们！
Come on in!
快请进
WiII you stop that?!
快停下吧
Ladies and gentIemen, Iet me welcome you
女士们先生们 欢迎你们
and thank you for your understanding and your patience.
感谢你们的理解和长久的支持
WeIcome to our new home
欢迎来到我们的新家
and Iet me drink to the heaIth of the hostess.
为女主人的健康干杯
I think the visit is over.
我觉得拜访就到此为止吧
Wait! See that?
等一下 看那边
- Let´s go! -Why?
- 快走！ - 怎么了？
That´s Saska.
那是萨诗卡
So what? She´s stiII aII his.
那又怎么样？ 她还是他的
You pig!
你这头猪
A friend´s wife is sacred.
朋友的妻子是不可以亵渎的
It´s Iike a hoIy cow to an Indian.
就像一头神圣的母牛对于印度人一样
- I´m no Indian, you idiot! - Cut it out. Let´s go!
- 我不是印度人，你这个傻瓜 - 别看了 快走吧
If Pirin saw us here, he´d beat us up,
要是皮林看到我们在这里 他会打我们的
poke our eyes and kick our asses!
戳我们的眼睛 踢我们的屁股
Hey! You hooIigans! What are you up to?
嘿！你们两个流氓 在那上面干什么呢？
I can see you! Come on out, gigoIIos!
我看见你们了！快出来吧 小白脸
Come cIoser! Don´t be shy!
再过来点  别害羞啊
Hand me my cIothes.
把我的衣服递给我
And cIose your eyes, pIease. Both of you!
把眼睛闭上 两个人都闭上
Put it on the rock,
把衣服放在石头上
and turn around. Both of you!
两个人都转过身去
Don´t you dare peeking.
别偷看啊
-Where´s Pirin? - He´s on a date. I gave him a day off.
- 皮林上哪去了 - 约会去了 我给他放一天假
PIease sit. I´II serve on you.
你坐着吧 我会端过去的
Interesting! What an originaI idea.
真有趣 多有创意的想法啊
Hey, Saska?
嘿 萨诗卡
- Don´t teII Pirin... - Don´t teII what?
- 别告诉皮林... - 别告诉他什么？
Don´t telI him we spied on you.
别告诉他我们看到你了
AII men are the same, they Iike to watch!
所有的男人都一样 就喜欢偷看
Perhaps this was the moment we realIy accepted her
也许就在这时 我们接受了她
Iike our own sister.
像我们的妹妹一样
We started teaching her new things,
我们开始教她一些新东西
when peopIe hang on the same rope
当大家都系在一根绳子上
with the other´s Iife in their hands.
手中握着另一个人的生命
You must have three stabIe points: Two feet and a hand, or the other way around.
你必须有三个支撑点： 两只脚和一只手 或是反过来
- Three stabIe points is the ruIe. - One is enough for me.
- 三个支撑点就是原则 - 我只用一个就够了
I wonder who gave the names to these hiIIs.
我很想知道是谁给这些山取的名字
Like that one... Frog Horse!
就像那一座... 蛙马
-Why? - They must have named it after you.
- 为什么呢？ - 它们肯定是以你命名的
What a view!
多美的风景啊
How can I heIp you?
我能帮你什么吗？
Two cognacs. The best you´ve got.
两杯科涅克白兰地 你们这最好的酒
- Here you are. - One´s for you, madam!
- 给 - 一杯是给你的 夫人
I don´t drink, sorry.
我不会喝酒 不好意思
Our coIIeague doesn´t drink on duty.
我们的同事不陪人喝酒
Thanks. Cheers!
谢谢 干杯！
Saska was not to bIame that there were other men.
这不怪萨诗卡 总有那么一些男人
They were aII over her.
围着她转
So what if the guests Iike her?
所以 要是有客人喜欢她的话
It´s good for the business.
对生意是有好处的
To heII with that! My wife is not some...
去死吧 我妻子又不是...
I just can´t stand it.
我受不了啦
What is it you can´t stand?
你受不了什么？
You smiIe and Iisten to that stupid taIk.
你笑着听那些愚蠢的谈话
Do you Iike it? You´re a married woman!
你喜欢那样吧？ 你是一个有丈夫的女人
- ShouId I stop taIking to peopIe? - Not to peopIe, to men.
- 那我不能和别人说话了？ - 不是所有人 只是男人
What do you want from me? I´m not dumb!
那你要我怎么做？ 我又不是哑巴
Do as you pIease! It´s up to you.
随你的便吧 由你决定
AII right. I think you´II be happy.
好吧 我想你会高兴的
Where´s the soup pIease?
我要点儿汤
WiIl be right there.
就在那边吗？
Oh and do you know what shouId the weather be Iike today?
还有 请问你觉得今天天气怎样？
Oh, thanks. I understand.
哦 谢谢 我知道了
PartIy cloudy. Thanks a Iot.
局部地区有云 谢谢你
Did you see? So pretty and such a tragedy.
你看到了吗？ 她那么漂亮真是可惜了
Excuse me... PIease.
打扰了 请
-Was she born Iike that? - She was born out of wedIock.
- 她生下来就这样吗？ - 她是私生子
An unknown tourist Ieft her in the hiIIs.
一个不知名的游客把她留着这儿的
- The child was raised by a mother bear... - TerribIe!
- 她是被一头母熊养大的 - 真可怕
She never Iearned to speak. - Just Iike Tarzan.
她从没学过说话 - 就像泰山一样！
Enjoy your meaI.
请用餐吧
A she-bear? What a great story!
一头母熊？ 多好的故事啊
But out of wedIock is too much.
但私生子就过分了
- Why? It adds some thriII. - Besides, it´s true.
- 为什么？增加一点刺激性嘛 - 再说了 这是事实
- What´s true? - That my parents were not married.
- 什么是事实？ - 我父母就是没结婚
- Why haven´t you toId me? - What?
- 你怎么没跟我说过？ - 什么？
That you don´t know your father.
就是关于你父母的事儿啊
l forgot. It´s not that important is it?
我忘了 而且也不重要 不是吗？
It isn´t but I want to know everything about you.
是不重要 但我想知道关于你的一切
You´re a man and men never need to know much.
你是男人 男人从来不用知道太多的
- I don´t like this. -What?
- 我不喜欢这样 - 不喜欢什么？
Like pretending she´s dumb.
假装她是个哑巴
lt´s crueI.
这很残忍
Pirin is right about that one.
皮林这么做是对的
You can´t give a woman too much freedom or you´II turn her into a sIut.
你不能给一个女人太多自由 否则她会变成一个荡妇的
Enough of that. Go to sIeep!
别说了 快睡吧
Maybe I´m wrong but I have a feeling
也许我错了 但我有一种感觉
that Pirin is not doing justice to this big Iove of his.
皮林在他的爱情方面不公平
Big Iove!
他的爱情
Should I envy or pity him?
我是该嫉妒还是该可怜他呢？
Since their wedding, Saska has not gone down to town once.
自从他们结婚以后 萨诗卡就没有进过一次城
She´s spent aII summer in the vaIIey.
她在山谷里度过了整个夏天
With caIm autumn days she started going on mysterious trips.
秋天的时候 她开始悄悄的外出了
HAVING MY HAIR DONE
我去做头发了
What do you think?
你看怎么样？
You don´t Iook Iike you.
看起来不像你了
Where have you been?
你去哪了？
I was craving sweets.
我想吃甜的
Seven hours up and down for three oranges?
爬七个小时的山就为了三个橙子？
I´ve eaten two on the way. Catch!
我在路上吃了两个 接着！
CouId you say thank you?
你们就不会说谢谢吗？
I think she´s seeing someone down there.
我觉得她是下山去见谁了
What do you think?
你们怎么看？
What shouId we say?
我们该说什么呢？
You´re the one sleeping with her.
跟她睡的人是你
I don´t feeI sure about anything anymore...
我很肯定
What shouId I do?
我该怎么办？
Nothing. Give it some time.
什么也别做 再等等看
If she´s cheating on you, you´II find out.
如果她红杏出墙的话 你会发现的
And go on from there.
然后再重新开始
There isn´t anyone Iike her. Anyone eIse.
没有人会再像她一样 没有人
Soon we go back to town. You´II spend winter together.
马上我们就要回城里了 你们整个冬天都会待在一起
Everything is going to be alI right.
一切都会好起来的
- Do you think so? - Sure
- 你真这么想吗？ - 是的
Why wouId she be cheating? Three months after the wedding?
她为什么要不忠于你呢？ 你们才结婚三个月
WeIl... I´ve heard stories...
这个嘛...我听过类似的事...
She´s young... She gets bored.
她那么年轻...在这又很无聊
Give her a bunch of kids. That´II keep her occupied.
让她生孩子吧 那会让她有事做的
She said she won´t Ieave again.
她说她不会再离开了
But I don´t trust her anymore.
但我不再相信她了
GentIemen, cream of mushroom today. What do you say?
先生们，今天做蘑菇汤 怎么样？
What wiII the excuse be tomorrow?
明天的借口是什么？
- What excuse? - What is it going to say tomorrow?
- 什么借口？ - 明天要怎么说？
And the day after? What wiII you crave then?
后天呢？你又想吃什么？
Not sure yet.
谁知道呢
You don´t beIieve me. Why don´t you tie me up?
你不信任我 为什么不干脆把我捆起来
I pIayed dumb before, I can pIay a dog on a leash too.
我以前扮过哑巴 我还能扮拴着的狗
That´s not what I meant.
我不是那个意思
Why do you never teII me you´re going out?
你怎么都不跟我说一声就出去呢？
I aIways Ieave a message.
我都有留下口信啊
And l aIways come back.
而且我都会回来
If you want to spy on me, maybe one day I won´t come back.
如果你想跟踪我的话 说不定哪天我就不回来了
Pirin didn´t see it was futiIe.
皮林没意识到那是徒劳的
Saska is a butterfIy- and he caught it.
萨诗卡就像被皮林捉住的一只蝴蝶
But he cannot cIose her in his hands.
但他不能一直把她捏在手里
He´s picking up the money. Our Iast pay checks.
他拿到了我们最后的薪水
Too bad. I couId stay the winter...
真可惜 我冬天也想待在这...
I couIdn´t. It´s too coId.
我到不想 冬天太冷了
And you Ieave footsteps. Any officer wiII catch you in no time.
你留下了脚印 警察可以随时抓到你
Hey Iazy bones! Have you heard?
嘿 懒骨头们 你们听说了吗？
- What´s the news? - We´re throwing a party tonight.
- 什么消息？ - 我们今晚要开个PARTY
- What party? - AfareweII party.
- 什么party？ - 告别party
And try to shave. I onIy dance with gentIemen.
别忘了刮胡子 我只和绅士跳舞
Does he know about the party?
他知道我们要开party吗？
It´s a surprise. He must have gotten heId up.
这是个惊喜 他肯定是被什么事给缠住了
Madam...
小姐
Excuse me.
我来
ShaII we dance?
你愿意和我跳一支舞吗？ 好的
You Iook beautifuI, Saska!
你看起来真漂亮 萨诗卡
I haven´t danced since my wedding.
结婚以后我就再没有跳过舞了
This is something!
这真不错
- What the heII are you doing? - Don´t disturb pIease. There´s a party here.
- 你们在干嘛呢？ - 别打断我们 我们在开party呢
On invitation onIy. ShaII we invite him?
只有邀请到的人才能参加 我们该请他吗？
Who is it?
他是谁？
The mister you´re sIeeping with.
和你睡的人
No, that´s not my husband.
不 这不是我丈夫
My husband greets everyone,
我丈夫会和每个人打招呼
and kisses the Iadies´ hands.
还会亲吻女士的手
- What´s up with him? - He´s mad we started without him.
- 他怎么了？ - 他生气我们没有等他就开始了
PIease!
请！
My oId song!
我最喜欢的歌
ShaII we dance?
我们能跳个舞吗？
You go dance with your doctor!
你去和你的医生跳吧！
With who?
谁？
You don´t know any doctors right?
你不认识任何医生吧？
I know about a thousand doctors. Which one do you have in mind?
我可知道几千个医生 你说的是谁呢？
The one you´ve taken for your Iover!
就是做你情人的那个！
What´s wrong with you? Are you drunk?
你怎么了？喝醉了？
Stay!
别走
I want my friends to see what my wife is Iike.
我想让我的朋友看看 我妻子到底是一个什么样的人
You don´t know your wife yourseIf!
你自己都不了解你妻子
How Iong has this been going on?
你和他在一起多久了？
Speak!
说啊！
I want to know everything. Where did you meet?
我想知道一切 你们在哪见面？
How often?
多久见一次？
Have you Iost your tongue?
你不会说话吗？
- Don´t, Saska! Stop! - He taught me...
- 别这样 萨诗卡 快停下 - 这是他教我的
If you cheated on me, I´lI...
要是你背着我偷人的话 我就...
KiII me?
杀了我？
If you don´t trust me, go ahead.
如果你不信任我的话 随你的便吧
KiII me.
把我杀了吧
Knock three times when you come to apoIogize.
要是你想道歉的话 就敲三下门
Maybe I´II forgive you because I know how much you Iove me.
也许我会原谅你 因为我知道你是爱我的
Good night.
晚安
I don´t get it.
我不明白
If she Iied, she wouId not be so bold, so sure...
要是她撒谎的话 她不会那么大胆 那么肯定...
They saw her.
他们看到她了
She meets him at the hospitaI.
去医院里和他见面
Let it be now, get some sIeep.
别想了 睡会儿吧
I can´t think of anything eIse.
我无法想任何事
How shouId we act around her?
那我们该怎么做呢？
If you´re my friends, treat her as a whore!
如果你们还是我朋友的话 对她就像对一个婊子一样吧！
l don´t understand. They´re like gypsies...
我真是不理解 他们就像吉普赛人
First they nearIy kiII each other, then they make up, they go to bed,
开始他们想把对方杀了 接着他们和好了 一起睡觉
and go out together in the morning.
早上又一起出去
That´s true Iove... maybe.
也许... 这就是真爱
That´s not Iove, that´s marriage!
这不是爱情 这是婚姻
Love is the thing before. Then it´s just a pain in the neck.
起先是有爱情的 接着只剩下窒息般的痛苦了
That waII is too difficuIt for her.
那岩壁对她来说太难了
Not with Pirin. He promised to take her to Copper Iong ago.
对皮林就不一样了 他以前答应过带她去铜塔的
Come back! Something happened at the waII!
快回来！ 岩壁那出事了！
I can´t see Saska! Go get some heIp!
我看不到萨诗卡 快叫人来帮忙
And bring bandages, and the rope... everything!
带上绷带，安全绳... 所有能用的！
Copper Tower! Pirin and his wife!
这里是铜塔 皮林和他妻子
- Move it, boys! Over! - I read you. Over!
- 快点小伙子们！结束 - 我知道了 结束
That´s terribIe. Look!
真可怕 快看
Christ! She feII from the walI.
上帝啊 她从岩壁上掉下来了
What is it? Can´t you knock?
谁啊？ 不会敲门吗？
I want to know what happened between you and my wife.
我想知道你和我妻子之间发生了什么
Who are you? What wife?
你是谁？ 什么妻子？
You must see a lot of women!
你肯定见过不少女人
Who do you think you are?
你认为你是谁？
I´m on caII. I don´t have time for private matters now.
我得去做事了 我没时间和你扯这些私事
Did you hear? The doctor is too busy
你们听到没有 医生说他很忙啊
to see us.
不能见我们
But you weren´t busy to see Saska?!
但你见萨诗卡就有时间了？！
So it´s you!
啊 原来就是你
Yes, it´s me.
是啊 是我
l had the feeIing...
我就知道...
... she´d have a husband Iike that, a guy who thinks he can soIve everything.
...她有个自认为能解决一切的老公
And brings his friends aIong for support...
还带着他的朋友来壮胆...
You know what? She was supposed to be my wife.
你知道吗？ 她本来应该是我妻子
You messed up her Iife, she canceIIed our engagement for you.
你毁了她的生活， 她为了你取消了我们的婚约
And you keep her in your rathoIe Iike your servant.
你却把她关在你那老鼠洞里 对她就像对一个仆人
You stoIe her from me and you´Il give her back to me!
你把她从我这偷走了 把她还给我！
Those two were fighting for a dead woman.
这两个人为一个死去的女人打着
The Copper Tower kept its victim.
铜塔留下了它的牺牲品
The hiIIs refused to Iet our friend bury her with due respect.
群山不让我的朋友 以体面的方式埋葬她
Everything got covered in snow.
一切都被白雪覆盖了
Saska was never found and she´II never return.
萨诗卡永远都没有被找到 她也永远回不来了
It was time,
是时候了
and we returned to our vaIIey as migrating birds.
我们像北归的候鸟 又回到了山谷
And we were Ioaded with a burden.
我们都担着重担
Pirin was sentenced to 14, VaIér and me to 10 months
皮林被判了14个月 瓦勒和我被判了10个月
for physicaI harm. On probation, IuckiIy.
因为故意伤害罪 很幸运 判了缓刑
May I?
可以吗？
Are you nuts? You threw 500 crowns away.
你疯了吗？你把500元扔了
I´II pay it back.
我会还你的
To heII with your money. I want my radio.
去你的钱 我要我的收音机
That was Saska´s song.
那是萨诗卡的歌
As for the radio....
至于你的收音机...
I´m sorry. I´Il buy you a new one.
对不起了 我会给你买一个新的
And one more thing. SmuggIing is over.
还有一件事儿 不可以在走私了
Why?
为什么？
We´re on probation for three years, remember?
我们被判了三年的缓刑 不记得了？
If they catch you, we aII go with you.
要是他们抓住你了 我们都要和你一起去坐牢了
ShaII I wait three years?
那我要等三年吗？
How can we pay for the doctor´s office?
我们拿什么赔医生的医药费？
And damages to the doctor?
还有那些砸坏的东西
How?
怎么赔？
Stop it.
行了
TilI I find my wife and bury her properIy.
直到我找到我妻子 并给她举行一个葬礼
They´re up aIready. Fine chaps.
他们都长大了 那些帅小伙们
I´ve known them since we were kids. l Iove to watch them cIimb.
我们还是孩子的时候就认识了 我喜欢看他们爬山
I wonder if they got permission for the cross.
我不知道他们有没有获得批准 把那个十字架树在那
That´s none of our business.
那不关我们的事
They´re nice guys, but they´II pay for VaIer sooner or Iater.
他们都是好人 但他们总有一天会为瓦勒付出代价的
And the sad job began.
悲伤的工作开始了
Pirin was Iooking for his woman.
皮林在找他的妻子
He wanted to force the mountains to give what was Ieft of her.
他想要大山把她妻子的遗骸还给他
He suffered quietIy.
他静静的忍受着一切
I was gIad when he sent me to town to buy a new radio for VaIer.
他让我上街给瓦勒买新收音机的时候 我很高兴
One more!
再来一杯
l heard you put up a cross.
我听说你们树起了一个十字架
Right.
是的
First he kiIIs, then he mourns!
他先把她杀了 接着又为她哀悼
Do you think that Pirin...
你认为皮林他...
Do you want to get beaten up?!
你想挨打吗？
Me? PeopIe taIk.
不是我 大家都这么说
I just Iisten.
我只是听到他们说而已
Can you read, Scabby?
你识字吧 史咖比？
There was a report written up on the accident.
这有一份事故报告
Pirin had bad Iuck, that´s aII.
皮林只是倒霉罢了  就这样
Reports... papers!
报告... 只是一张纸而已！
The paper says one thing, the rock saw another thing.
纸上写的是一回事儿 岩石看到的是另一回事
You weren´t there!
你又不在那！
Pirin couId never do such a thing.
皮林绝不会那么做的！
How do you know what one is capabIe of?
你怎么知道一个人能干出什么事儿来？
Scabby! You son of a deviI!
史咖比！你这个邪恶之徒
We spent alI Pirin´s money on drinks.
我们把皮林的钱都拿来喝酒了
It wasn´t your money, what´s the harm?
又不是你的钱 你又没什么损失
l have to buy a radio!
我还得买收音机呢！
Don´t worry.
别担心
Scabby can heIp you.
我会帮你的
-What´s this? - The radio.
- 这是什么？ - 收音机
Are you drunk?
你喝醉了？
Where did you get it?
你上哪弄来的？
I´m not sure...
我也不是很清楚...
You shouIdn´t have sent me to town.
你不该让我进城的
I´II burn it, or I´Il chop it up for firewood
我要烧了它或是把它劈开做柴火
together with the scabby fooI!
连同史咖比那个傻瓜一起
It works.
这东西能用
Sure it does. I don´t buy junk.
当然能用  我不会买个垃圾回来
Too bad we can´t take it up to the hut.
真可惜我们不能把它搬到山上去
Who says?
谁说的？
You´II sweat the boose out of your system.
你来把它背上去
Hey, what the heII do we need this for?
嘿 我们要这玩意儿做什么？
What the heII did you buy it for? Shut up and keep going!
那你买它干嘛？ 你给我闭嘴 接着走
I´Il remember that hike as Iong as I Iive.
我一辈子都记得这次徒步旅程
l was swearing every step I took.
我每走一步都在发誓
I cursed Scabby and myseIf.
我诅咒史咖比和我自己
Why did I agree to go see
为什么我要同意去那个教堂
the church and have mass wine too?
并喝的一塌糊涂
To heII with it! You carry the thing!
妈的！你得抬着这东西！
The moon is bright,
月亮很亮
we can waIk at night too.
我们夜里也能接着走
No way.
不可能
Just push a IittIe, press down,
只要轻轻的推一下 推下去
a second is enough and the burden is gone.
只要一秒钟的时间 重担就消失了
Who knows, maybe Pirin did the same thing on Copper Tower.
谁知道呢 也许皮林 在爬铜塔时也是这么做的
Move your foot.
我们动脚吧
Get up! Let´s go!
起来！走！
Are you guys nuts?!
你们两个疯了吗？
It´s yours.
这是你的
We brought this for you.
我们给你买的
- You threw away a radio, not a... - AII right, aII right...
- 你扔的是我的收音机，不是一个... - 是的 是的
I won´t throw this away.
我不会把这个扔了的
Anyone can have a radio.
人人都可以有收音机
You wiII have a harmonium.
你却有一架脚踏风琴
We used to have one at home.
我家以前有一架
Mom soId it when my father Ieft us.
当我爸爸离开我们的时候 我妈把它卖了
What was that?
那是什么声音？
It sounded Iike shooting at the border.
听起来像边境那边传来的枪声
It was a sad job.
真是个让人伤心的活儿
I´m not sure it was necessary.
我不确定是否必要
Maybe it´s better to remember peopIe the way they were.
也许记住一个人生前的样子更好
But Pirin wiII never find peace before finding his wife.
但皮林一天找不到他妻子 他就一天不安心
Look!
看那
What is it?
那是什么？
Blood.
是血
What happened?
发生了什么事？
I knew you´d freak out.
我知道你们都吓坏了
Nothing happened.
没什么
Everything´s aII right. Those dummies don´t know how to shoot.
一切都好好的 那些傻子不知道怎么开枪
I toId you to stop.
我让你别干了
Be quiet. Go wipe the bIood from the stairs.
别说了 去把楼梯上的血擦了
To heII with this!
去他的
- Can you waIk? - Sure I can!
- 你还能走吗？ - 当然能
Lord, such bad Iuck! For two pairs of stupid shoes!
上帝啊 真倒霉 就为了两双鞋子
- Who was shooting? Our guys? - No, it was the PoIish!
- 谁开的枪？我们的人？ - 不 是波兰人
And I swear I was on our side by then!
我确定我当时已经在我们国家境内了
How can some stupid foreigners
那些愚蠢的外国人怎么能
shoot SIovaks Iike rabbits!
把我们斯洛伐克人当兔子来打呢？
Shut up and Iie down!
别说了 快躺下吧
What do you need this for?
你要这些干什么?
I need it to study and Iearn right?
我要看着乐谱学啊
- And the shoes? - Ijust took them aIong.
- 还有这些鞋子？ - 我只是想要这些东西
You can´t Iive on music.
你不能只靠音乐活着啊
Where are they?
他们在哪？
- HeIIo boys! - Hi, Feri.
- 小伙子们 你们好 - 你好 费利
- Hi, VaIer. - Hi, officer.
- 你好 瓦勒 - 你好 长官
What a renaissance taIent you are.
你真有天赋啊
Where have you been today, guys?
你们今天都干嘛了，伙计们
As usuaI. Under the Copper.
像往常一样 在铜塔下面呢
We were searching aII day.
我们在那找了一天
- AlI three of you? - Sure.
- 你们三个都在那吗？ - 是啊
-Who Iooked after the hut? - Nobody. We took a day off!
- 那谁看着小屋呢？ - 没人看着 我们都去了
ShaII we do a search?
我们能搜查一下吗？
Have you got a warrant?
你们有搜查证吗？
I can do it without a warrant if I want to.
我没搜查证照样能搜查
I know.
我知道
Six.
六
WeII! A PoIish score!
喔 一本波兰的乐谱
When was the Iast time you´ve been there?
你上次去那边是什么时候？
Some fifteen years ago.
十五年前吧
It was a schooI trip you see.
是学校组织的旅行
The teacher heId my hand, so I would not be scared of the PoIes.
老师牵着我的手 那样我就不用害怕波兰人了
And you haven´t visited there today?
你今天没有到那边去吗？
What for? Grass is greener on this side of the fence.
我去那边干嘛？ 这边风景不是更好？
Very funny! You´II stop joking soon enough.
真有趣 你们一会就不想开玩笑了
AII of you, comrades. You too.
你们每个人 包括你
Have you got permission for the cross?
你有立十字架的批准吗？
TeII him to shut up! If he mentions the cross again, I´II...
让他闭嘴 要是他再提十字架的话 我就...
There´s nothing wrong about the cross.
这不关十字架的事儿
Let it be. Everything´s fine.
就让它在那吧 没事的
Just that this morning the Polish wounded a man
只是今天上午波兰人开枪打伤了一个
who then crossed the border to here.
偷越边境的人
-WouId you know anything about it? - No.
- 你们知道些什么吗？ - 不知道
That´s what I thought, as usuaI.
就像我想的一样 和平常一样
WeIl then. Good night, boys. And see you Iater, VaIer.
那就这样了 晚安 小伙子们 晚点见 瓦勒
- Your majesty! - You fooI!
- 是的 陛下 - 你这个傻瓜
He needs to catch someone.
他需要抓个人
He wants a promotion...
他想升职...
Good for him.
对他有好处
Pirin searched aIone today since dawn.
今天天亮以后 皮林就一个人在找着
I stayed to take care of VaIer.
我留下来照顾瓦勒
SuddenIy an unexpected guest turned up.
突然 一个意料之外的客人来了
- What does he want? - He´s waiting for Pirin.
- 你想怎么样？ - 他在等皮林
-Why? - It´s none of your business!
- 为什么？ - 这不关你的事
You haven´t got enough?
你还不满足吗？
If he sees you here, you´II end up in hospitaI, and we go to prison.
要是他看见你在这 你会被打得进医院的 我们会进监狱
Let bygones be bygones.
过去的就让它过去吧
Here you are. Have a drink and go.
给 喝完就走吧
Come on! SIap him so he´d buzz off!
来吧 把他打的眼冒金星
I´m staying here and I´m going to talk to him.
我要待在这 并告诉他
What about, damn it? The woman is dead!
告诉他什么？ 妈的 那女的都死了
- Let the dead rest in peace! - The dead, yes, not the Iiving.
- 让死者安息吧 - 死者 是啊 不是活着的人
You aImost crippIed me. And what for?
你差点把我打瘸了 那又是为什么呢？
There was nothing between me and his wife.
我和他妻子之间根本就没有什么
What do you mean? You were seeing each other, she went to meet you!
你是什么意思？ 你们一直在幽会 她去找你的
I wanted her to get a divorce, and come back to me.
我要她离婚 然后回到我身边
-What about her? - She asked me to let her go.
- 那她怎么说？ - 她让我放她走吧
She said she´d never Ieave him.
她说她绝不会离开皮林的
She asked me to forgive and forget.
她让我原谅并忘了她
And to Iet her Iive her Iife.
让她过她想要的生活
That´s aII right. I knew it!
这就对了 我早知道
Nothing´s aII right! Have you heard the rumours?
根本就不对 你没听见谣传吗？
Do you beIieve it?
那你相信吗？
It was an ordinary accident at Copper Tower. Understand?
那只是在铜塔发生的一场事故 你懂吗？
It was an ordinary murder. l know he kiIIed her because of me.
那是谋杀 我知道他因为我而杀了萨诗卡
I don´t want to see the Iook in his eyes when I teII him he kiIIed for no reason.
我不想看到他眼里的痛苦 当我告诉他他杀了一个无辜的人时
- Is this what you came here for? - Yes.
- 你来这就是为了这个？ - 是的
I´Il teII him so he can go on with a happy Iife.
我要告诉他 这样他才能快乐的活下去
You wiII never teIl him about this, doc.
你绝不可以告诉他这些 医生
You got one minute to get up and Ieave.
你有一分钟的时间离开这里
I know where to find her now.
我知道在哪能找到她了
That was the worst part, knowing she may stiII be aIive.
这真痛苦 知道她可能还活着
There was an accident and your wife is dead.
事故发生了 你妻子死了 就是这样
It was not an accident.
那不是一场事故
I kiIIed her and you know it.
你知道 是我杀了她
I didn´t trust her, I feIt I wouId kiII her.
我不信任她 我觉得我该杀了她
I resisted, by it was in my bIood.
我尽力不去想 但它始终萦绕在我脑海里
She feII off the walI and I could not save her.
她从岩壁上坠落了 我救不了她
The rope burned my hands, but I heId on.
绳子像烧着了一样 但我还是坚持拉着
Then it jerked... and it was over.
接着 猛地一下... 一切都结束了
The rope reaIIy broke?
绳子真的断了？
WeIl yes. Otherwise she wouIdn´t have faIIen.
是的 否则她是不会掉下去的
Then you didn´t do it!
那就不是你杀了她
You did not kiII her, man!
你没有杀她 兄弟
My thoughts kiIIed her. AIl that was inside of me.
我的那种想法杀了她 我心里的魔鬼
Have you gone mad?
你疯了吗？
Maybe it was there inside of you but you didn´t kiII her!
也许你那么想过 但你确实没杀她
Do you hear me?
你听到我说的了吧？
Accidents happen aIl the time.
事故随时都会发生
You don´t know. Maybe she was better off, faIIing Iike that.
你不知道 也许她那样掉下去更好
Maybe I reaIIy wouId have kiIIed her one day.
也许搞不好哪天我也会杀了她
You had no reason!
你没理由杀她啊
She never cheated on you. Never.
她从来没有背叛过你 从来没有
How do you know?
你怎么知道？
I just do.
我就是知道
The other guy was here today and he toId us the truth.
那个人今天来了 他告诉了我们真相
he was a good wife and she Ioved no one eIse but you.
她是个好妻子 她只爱你一个人
Are you nuts?
你疯了吗？
Sick peopIe need fresh air.
病人需要呼吸新鲜空气
And musicians need a good echo.
音乐家需要好的和声
See? This is a reaI echo. Understand?
听到没？ 这才是真正的和声 懂不？
If Pirin were here, he wouIdn´t Iet you.
要是皮林在这的话 他是不会让你这么做的
Why didn´t you go with him? I´d get some peace and quiet.
你为什么不和他一起去？ 我更想一个人安静待着
He didn´t wake me up.
他没把我叫醒
He may find Saska today. And he wants to do it aIone.
他今天也许能找到萨诗卡 他想一个人做
- And I need to take care of you. - My words. Do it.
- 我还得照顾你 - 那好 照顾吧
EngIish breakfast pIease.
给我准备一份英式早餐吧
Wounded peopIe need caIories.
受伤的人需要补充能量
Do you want me to scratch your butt too?
那你要我也帮你抓抓屁股吗？
Maybe Iater.
也许 一会儿
VaIer!
瓦勒！
Pirin...
皮林...
He went to kiII himseIf.
他想要自杀
Good-bye, my boys. We won´t meet again.
永别了 我亲爱的伙伴们 我们不会再见面了
When you find my wife, bury us side by side.
你们找到我妻子时 把我们埋在一起
Your good friend, Jozo BeIej.
你们的好朋友 卓佐・贝勒
No! I won´t Iet him! It won´t happen!
不！我不让他这么做 我不让他死
Do something!
快想想办法！
I won´t Iet him!
我不让他死！
Pirin!
皮林！
Don´t do it! You can´t!
别那么做！ 你不能那么做！
He´s stiII aIive.
他还活着
Shut up! Every minute is precious. FIy Iow above him.
闭嘴！时间很宝贵 快飞过来靠近他
Come back, Pirin!
快回来 皮林！
Buddy!
好伙计！
Pirin, I won´t Iet you!
皮林！ 我不让你死！
Not Iike that! Not with dogs!
别过来！别用狗！
No dogs! I can´t stand that.
别用狗！我讨厌狗！
There´s no point, don´t be siIIy.
那是没有意义的 别傻了
VaIer, we´ve got evidence.
瓦勒 我们有证据
Come then, but onIy you.
过来 就你一人
Pirin has found what we are aII Iooking for.
皮林找到了我们都在追寻的
Peace for our souIs, justice for our deeds,
心灵的平静 对我们所作所为的公平判决
here, on this beautifuI and sad piece of Iand,
就在这块美丽又充满哀伤的土地上
which is our cradIe and our grave.
这里是我们的摇篮 也将是我们的坟墓